[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
now lille's theorem is really at the
heart of Quant of classical
mechanics it's at the heart of
hamiltonian classical
mechanics and a quantum mechanical
version of it which is called unitarity
is very much at the heart of quantum
mechanics it will profit us to
understand lille's
theorem uh because as I said it is the
immediate classical analog of one of the
most fundamental principles of physics
quantum
mechanics um it can also be thought
of as the idea or generalization of the
idea of information conservation we
talked about this I think in the first
lecture where let me just remind you I
think I've done this a couple of times
but let me remind you again uh that if
you have a phase space which consists of
a collection of points by the phase
space I simply mean the space of
possible uh
configurations of a system in the case
of a mechanical system it would be
positions and velocity these in the case
of just a system with a finite number of
states it would be any one of those
finite number of states and then the
laws of Mechanics for this very simple
setup would simply be expressed as a
rule for going from any uh configuration
to any other
configuration and um I can draw it in a
more complicated way but there's not
much
point I could draw s of the lines cross
but that doesn't add anything to it
you could have some disconnected
Cycles but generally that's the
pattern and you'll notice that each
point has one Arrow coming into it and
one Arrow going out of
it that's the basic idea of information
conservation that nothing gets lost
there's no let's call it
convergence or
Divergence of the flow in the phase
space this can be thought of as a kind
of
flow uh what's what's what's the word
for what they do in discos where they
flash lights at you stroboscope strob
you could think of it stroboscopically
where each instant uh you flash and the
system moves to the next configuration
so it's a sort of stroboscopic uh flow
of the points in the face
space but um you could imagine
populating each of these points
populating means imagine a
system at that point in Phase space
undergoing the motion that the system is
supposed to have so we would have a
collection of systems filling up the
phase space one at each point in the
phase space and as time evolves the
points in the phase space just move
have described this I think probably the
best way to describe it is in that they
move
incompressible among other things that
means that if you start with a separate
point a separate system at each point in
the phas space you'll never wind up with
two points or two systems at the same
point in the phase space it's not like
playing Monopoly where the Monopoly men
can wind up on the same uh on the same
square that never happens they stay
distinct from each
other uh the points in the phase
space they don't diverge they don't
converge what would diverge mean diverge
would be a situation where an incoming
line would split in two now what would
that mean that would mean there was some
ambiguity in the evolution of the system
if it went from here to here it wouldn't
know where to go next sometimes it might
go this way sometimes it might go that
way that doesn't happen so there's no
Divergence of the flow and there's also
no convergence of the flow convergence
would mean that from two different phase
points you come to the same phase point
then you would always know where to go
but you wouldn't know where you came
from if you found yourself over here you
wouldn't know if you came from here or
over
here uh those are the Forbidden kinds of
flows as I said you can think of
a lack of convergence or Divergence on a
phase Bas
yeah it's quite
thinkable it's not that it's not
thinkable to have these things they
don't occur in classical physics they
don't occur except in so far as you
ignore things except in so far as you
ignore degrees of
freedom um
as I've said over and over friction is
an example where you start a system in
any number of ways you start in many
ways it comes to the same
configuration well not quite but uh you
get the
idea friction just slows things down
brings them to rest no matter how they
start they come to rest many many
different configurations can wind up
exactly the
same but that's only because you've
ignored things you've ignored the
molecular structure of a of a
tabletop um you can take this as an
experimental fact or you can take it as
a consequence of the basic rules of
quantum mechanics but all the classical
mechanical systems that are of interest
in fundamental physics have the property
that there's no Divergence or
convergence
yeah yes it is saying something more
than that it is saying something more
than that and we'll see we'll see what
it says it's what leoville theorem is
what it
says
uh but we'll come to it for example the
sort of thing that can't happen is
here's phase space
okay every point in this phase space is
distinct from every other point in some
sense now you could take a group of
points and follow them and they might
all squeeze together into a smaller
volume right that's the kind of
convergence that doesn't
happen instead the flow in Phase space
is a kind of incompressible flow both
incompressible what's the opposite of
compression and non- Divergent
well phase space doesn't blow up it
doesn't shrink but we we'll come to with
a precise definition of it soon
enough
uh so in some sense the phase space
doesn't pinch together or divert
it's as though here's the way you can
think about
it in the Continuum mechanics case you
can imagine
populating the phase space let's call it
P and q q and
P and of course there may be many p's
and q's I simply can't draw them on the
Blackboard and we might imagine in the
same way that we populated each point
here with a system we can imagine
populating the phase space with a dust
with a the dust of
points and follow that dust of points
let's assume that the phase space is
populated uniformly with a constant
density a uniform density of points of
dust uh and we follow each point as it
moves through the phase space it defines
a kind of
flow but it defines a special kind of
flow which is called
incompressible and it basically has the
property that each point in the face
bace can be thought of as having a
little volume around
it each one occupies its own little
volume if we take the density to be
uniform then each one of these volumes
is the same and as we follow it when we
see it later each phase point is
separated from each other phase Point by
the same amount of volume in the phase
space or or you can say it another way
if you take a group of points there are
three ways to say it all of them
equivalent the first is to follow
individual points with little volumes
around them and watch them move okay uh
the volume of each little point or the
region occupied by that little little
Point stays the same but we can
generalize that we can say take any
region of the Subspace of the phase
space to begin with take any region and
follow its points follow its points with
time after time that phase space region
will change it'll change its shape some
points move faster in another
points uh it may spread one way it may
stretch some direction it may compress
in another Direction but the one thing
that's true is that the volume of that
region will stay the same in other words
the volume of a fixed set of points in
the phase
space will not
change connect and it will maintain
connectedness and it will maintain
connectedness absolutely they don't
disconnect the connectedness is simply
the predictability if it became
disconnected how could it become
disconnected a phase point would split
somehow which would simply mean it
didn't know where to go the equations
broke down at this point and didn't tell
a phase point where to go properly so
yeah regions maintain their
connectivity in other words a region
like this can't break up into two
disconnected
region and a hole cannot appear so it's
a very continuous smooth uh no holes the
the connectivity is conserved but the
type of connectivity simple simply
connectedness multiple connectedness
whatever it is the
topology of the chunk of phase space is
maintained as is its
volume what is not maintained in
general uh is the distance in the phase
space between
points take a pair of points in the
phase space and follow them if we follow
them we may discover later that they're
closer
together now you say how is that
consistent how is it possible that the
volume uh of a phase region doesn't
change but the distance between points
can change well what can happen for
example is a volume can stretch in One
Direction and compress in the other
direction volume being conserved the
volume of all of this collection of
points in here is unchanged but if you
follow each point you find mind that the
shape changes but the shape changes in a
way that leaves the volume unchanged but
in particular this point and this point
are now found here and here so they're
much further from each other than they
were on the other hand this point and
this point are found here and here so
they're much closer together than they
were
H points switch no no everything is
extremely
continuous conserves
orientation uh what is that
mean Oh you mean can one well you can
certainly have a situation where there's
a point in Phase space moving to the
right and another point in the phas
space moving to the right and they start
like this and this one is moving faster
than this one and uh passes it yes that
can happen no question that uh uh that
that can happen for
example you can have a situation where
if you started with a square in Phase
space that square could evolve into
a what is that
called parallel sare a parallelogram of
the same area that would happen for
example if the top was moving faster
than the bottom but uh the width of the
whole
thing that's a sort of sheer motion
where the top shears relative to the
bottom that's perfectly allowed that uh
that conserves the volume if the height
and the width stay the same conserves a
volume so that's possible and that would
certainly allow a point back here to get
ahead of a point over here yeah so
uh well go ahead ask the question yeah
what's that
yeah the double pendulum and a
gravitation yeah
neighborh absolutely absolutely but but
we yeah yeah we'll talk about that case
uh that is not a counter example to this
right it's
um an example of it but one which is
less smooth and less uh predictable but
for reasons we'll come
through
okay well let me just say it very
quickly I say the space maintains a
certain degree of connectivity it
maintains its connectivity all it
happens is shape changes but the shape
can change wildly for example this
sphere can evolve into something
with I'm trying to keep the volume the
same as it was before but I'm probably
not know horrible
uh
so the there's no rule that says that
the shape can't evolve into some wildly
extravagantly different uh structure
which eventually starts to look more and
more
fractal now it never really forms a
fractal because continuity tells you
that things which are close to each
other will stay close to each other but
in time it'll start to get more and more
fragmented more and more fractured uh
but always maintaining it volume okay
maintaining its volume so that
distinguishable points remain
distinguishable and a measure of
distinguishability is the volume
surrounding a point but
uh we will we will return to this
particular picture I ought to leave it
there because I'll probably wind up
drawing it again but uh not right
now that incidentally is the um basic
case of a chaotic system chaotic systems
do exactly this kind of
thing non-chaotic systems tend to
maintain a greater degree of shape
coherence we can call
it say it
again no they don't they don't stay in
close proximity no no no the statement
is the volume of the region in Phase
space is
maintained so what that tells you is
that if two
points do
diverge or let's say that if the phase
volume stretches in One Direction it
must compress in the other
direction okay so it's not completely
without
rules uh but the only only real rule is
that the phase volume is maintained as
time
evolves volume volume
means the same thing that it does in
calculus it means the integral it means
break up the region into a lot of
extremely small
cells Let's uh let's talk about area for
the moment let's not try to get to
higher dimensions for a minute let's
just take the case of one Q 1
P then what I mean by volume of phase
space is just the area of the region
regions have area irregardless of
whether they're squares they don't have
to be squares or rectangles to have area
uh you have to use a little bit of
calculus to add all of these up but
there's a well- defined notion of area
and as you follow it the shape may
change but the area doesn't now if it's
a higher dimensional system with more
than one p and Q incidentally as always
there's one Q for HP they come in they
come in
pairs but we simply have to think about
the higher dimensional version of volume
where we break up the volume into lots
of little cubes count the cubes and add
them
up yes
Michael yes absolutely that's right
nearby means close by in position and
momentum but it doesn't mean that they
stay close
by okay and in particular the chaotic
case is the situation where there's a
great deal of tendency for points which
are close to to each other to diverge
from each other but always at the
expense of Co of compression in some
other
direction
yeah
right where having which happen
now oh oh oh oh you said well yeah
that's that's basically friction you say
you say there are many ways to start and
you can wind up with a six on the table
yeah
right if you didn't have friction it
would just bounce off the table and uh
and uh uh rebound and it wouldn't stop
it wouldn't stop yeah yeah
right friction is incredibly common
right yes yes and when you're doing a a
mechanical system in practice if you're
an engineer you don't want to forget
friction if you're a physicist you often
want to forget friction you want to
pretend it didn't exist in fact in many
situations microscopic physics doesn't
have friction if you really follow every
degree of freedom of a system then
there's no concept of friction in the
equations friction is a collective
effect of many variables some of which
you just decide I'm going to
ignore uh so it's a thermodynamic idea
ra rather than a um an idea of basic
mechanics
of course they have to be consistent
with each other when you decide not to
look at a collection of degrees of
freedom the behavior of it may
nevertheless reflect the fact that in
some bigger
sense um the phase Space volume is
conserved uh energy conservation is one
which uh you might not realize if you
were sliding around things on the table
so energy is lost kinetic energy there's
no potential energy it doesn't go up or
down kinetic kinetic energy is just lost
looks like energy conservation is
wrong um those who would believe in
energy conservation would make a
prediction and the prediction would be
that if you very minutely and carefully
measure the temperature of the table the
temperature of the table will go up a
little bit and if you know the specific
heat of the table then you can find out
how much energy was absorbed by the
table etc etc and uh and conservation of
energy will tell you will tell you that
there must have been degrees of freedom
that you ignored the same is true of
this conservation of
information if you discover a system
which looks like the phase space is
Contracting it means you've left things
out of the
system now that's a that's an empirical
fact in the sense that it has always
proven to be the case
uh but by now it is uh a fundamental
fact derived from quantum mechanics but
let's take it as a uh well we're not
going to take lille's theorem as a given
we're going to prove it but we're going
to prove it from something we're going
to prove it from Hamilton's
equations all right so the beauty of the
hamiltonian form of
mechanics is this flow picture a flow in
pH space a very predictable flow in
Phase space where the points move in a
very characteristic kind of way and that
characteristic way is Hamilton's
equations the entire flow is determined
by a single function of all of the PS
and q's if you know that function then
you know the flow on the phase space and
if you started a little boat sailing on
the flow which means you start a system
at a particular point in the phase space
that hamiltonian flow will tell you
where it is at any future
time okay and that flow is
incompressible but let's uh let's um uh
first Define the
flow so this is Dynamics as a flow in
Phase space as a kind of fluid
flow all right so every Point has
associated with it a
motion that depends only on where you
are and a motion means means a Time
derivative this is p this is Q It Means
A P Dot and a q dot in other words a
velocity but not a usual velocity a
velocity in Phase space consisting of
the ordinary velocities which are the Q
dots plus the P dots which are the time
derivatives of the PS okay so we just
write down Hamilton's equations P sub I
dot is equal to minus d h by DQ subi
notice they come in
pairs is plus DH by DP d p
ofi that's it that's all of mechanics in
a nutshell in the hamiltonian
form
okay all right let's consider what it
means for a flow to be incompressible
what we're ultimately going to prove is
that this flow is
incompressible what exactly does it mean
let's start with a one-dimensional flow
and see what it says so a
one-dimensional flow just means you have
a line and let's populate that line with
a uniform distribution of
points for Simplicity I'm taking a
uniform distribution that means that the
density of points is the same everywhere
as along the line or equivalently the
little tiny separation between points is
uniform along the line what kind of
motion constitutes incompressible flow
well basically there's only one
kind and that's just all the points move
together with exactly the same velocity
what would happen if the velocity varied
from point to point along here for
example suppose it went faster over here
than over here then there would be a
clumping up of points in between okay
there would be a clumping up and a
increase in their density all right but
let's uh let's uh consider the
mathematics of
it what's
that yes yes but let's just talk about
flows for a minute for a minute let's
forget phase space and just talk about
the general concept of an incompressible
flow uh and we'll come back to phase
space as a special case that's right
you're no you're
right uh but uh nevertheless it's
possible to think of incompressible
flows in one dimension they're very
trivial all you can have any velocity
you like but the velocity has to be
completely uniform all across the line
otherwise there's a clumping now you can
think of it in two ways you can either
say take a set of points and follow them
let's take a connected set of points
like this and follow them one way of
saying incompressibility is just that
the volume of that particular set of
points stays the
same all right that's a view of it
following the points there's another
view of it which stays at a particular
place in
space let's say we take stay at a
particular space in place in space in
other words a little volume we're not
going to move that volume but points are
going to come into it and points are
going to depart from it if the fluid is
moving to the right of course it could
be moving to the right in some places in
the left and other places but let's
count all velocities as positive to the
right if
um if the fluid is moving then some
points leave this region and some points
enter the region to say it's
incompressible says that the number of
points that enters is the same as the
number of points that leaves in any
given uh time
interval what is the condition for that
well it's more or less obvious that that
if the velocity let's imagine that the
velocity is fast over here and slow over
here all right then it's quite clear
that the number of points that are
exiting the region is proportional to
the velocity at this end right let's
call this point 2 and point
one the number of points
exiting will be proportional to the
velocity of the points to the right and
that we can just call V2 that's the
number of points exiting the number of
points entering is the velocity at
one so the net increase shall we take
increase or decrease let's talk about
the net decrease the net decrease in
points in this volume here is going to
be proportional to V2 minus
V1 actually it's V2 minus V1 time the
density of the points but as long as the
density is
uniform then
uh
then we can just write that
the
yeah velocity High theity got to be
changing that's the
point that's the point that's exactly
the point wait if the velocity yeah if
the velocity is higher at this end or
whichever way if the velocity is bigger
at one end than the other then the
density inside has to be changing
incompressible means that the density is
not allowed to change okay okay so what
it says is that V2 minus V1 must be
equal to zero that it cannot be a
gradient or a variation of the Velocity
this must be equal to zero now if I take
a small interval let's let's imagine
that this is a small interval then the
difference of the Velocity at two and
one assuming everything is nice and
smooth and
differentiable the calculus applies for
a small interval we can say that the
difference of the velocities is just
proportional to the derivative of the
Velocity with respect to x times some
Delta X where Delta X is the uh is the
interval
here and then we would write that this
has to be equal to
zero Delta X is just a small interval
it's not zero it's just a number so it
follows then that the derivative of the
Velocity with respect to X must be equal
to zero for an incompressible fluid
which which is what we would intuitively
imagine that the whole fluid has to move
together since all of the motion is
along the x- axis I'm going to write
this as the derivative of the X
component of the Velocity there is only
an X component of the
Velocity but uh just uh
to use a notation which will generalize
I'll write that this is dvx by DX is
equal to zero that's the condition in
one dimension for an incompressible
fluid and it is very
trivial
questions good all right now let's move
on to two Dimensions I'm going to call
the two directions X and
Y why not X and
Y now let's ask in a small interval of
time what is the increase or the
decrease I guess uh V2 minus V1 would be
the decrease in the number of points
what is the decrease in the number of
points in this little square here let's
take the square to be of size Delta X
and Delta y it's not a square it's a
rectangle how many points are entering
and
leaving from on the various sides of
this uh uh rectangle all right let's
start with a number of points coming in
here again we're imagining that the
density is completely
uniform so the number of points per unit
area to start with to start with is
completely uniform if it's
incompressible then the number of points
per unit area must stay the same must be
exactly the same after afterwards so
okay so how many points come in from
this side here well the number of points
coming in this way per unit time is
clearly going to be proportional to the
X component of velocity the Y component
of velocity a velocity in the vertical
direction will not contribute to points
Crossing this boundary here so so the X
component of motion here
VX at the left hand end
here will constitute the
incoming points coming in from the left
vertical side of the
square what about the number going
out oh there's another Factor there's
another Factor anybody know what the
other factor
is Delta y yeah the size of the Y
interval here
obviously the bigger the Y interval for
a given velocity the more points will
enter there so there's another factor
which is just Delta
y now how about the number of points
going out on this
side that's also proportional to VX but
VX at the displaced
Point all right so we have to move ahead
a little bit and subtract the points
coming out on the side exactly what we
did over here the answer is going to be
the D derivative of VX with respect to
X time Delta y times Delta X where does
this Delta X come
from the difference of the Velocity here
and
here is the derivative of V with respect
to X time Delta
X right the difference between the X
component of velocity on the right hand
side of the square and on the left hand
side of the square is the derivative of
V with respect to X time Delta X we have
to multiply that by Delta y to find the
NIT number of points coming through this
coming into on this side minus out on
this side and that's
this okay so this is the net number of
points coming into the rectangle through
the vertical edges now what about the
horizontal edges the horizontal edges
things can also move in
but now the X component of velocity is
not relevant to particles coming in in
this Direction only the Y component of
the motion is relevant on the horizontal
boundaries so how many particles come in
from the lower end well that's going to
be V
suby at the lower end times Delta
X
but then we have to subtract off V suby
coming out of the top end
here in order to find the difference of
the incoming points and the outgoing
points on the bottom and top so that
will give us the derivative of Vy with
respect to what with respect to Y
because we're going from bottom to
top times Delta y
y the Whole Net
change in the number of points in this
rectangle is simply proportional to
Delta X Delta y that's just the area of
the little region times a quantity which
is called the Divergence of the Velocity
field this is the velocity field it can
vary from place to
place but it's definite and it's fixed
this is derivative of VX with respect to
X plus the derivative of Vy with respect
to
Y if this is positive it corresponds to
a decrease in the
density what if it's an incompressible
fluid if it's an incompressible fluid
then the net number of points coming in
and going out must add up to
zero all right we can forget the Delta x
* Delta y y that's just a number for a
little area and so the condition of
incompressibility is that the Divergence
of the Velocity field is equal to zero
let's drop this Factor here it doesn't
do anything for
us dvx by DX plus dvy by Dy is equal to
zero this is not a general rule about
all possible flows this is a rule about
incompressible
flows that start with uniform density
and maintain the uniformity of the
density notice that it does not say that
the velocity can't vary from place to
place but it does say that if the
velocity is increas if the X component
of velocity is increasing in One
Direction then the Y component must be
decreasing in the other direction so it
does not say that the
velocity can't change from place to
place it doesn't require the motion to
be just rigid motion
uh more more complicated kinds of things
can satisfy this kind of flow but uh it
is constrained in this
way okay questions
yes yeah but we we take an instantaneous
photograph of it and we ask at this
instant what's the time rate of change
of the number of points in here so at
any instant some something which is
coming in here yes it could it could
turn around and go up here that's
perfectly acceptable but that will be at
a later time that it'll be found found
going out here so we take imagine a
snapshot instantaneously right now what
is the time rate of change of the number
of points in this
volume okay so if a point is coming
through here it's not going out
there it applies to any number of
dimensions so in any number of
Dimensions we could
write there aren't enough letters in the
alphabet but uh I some X Y and Z here
just refer to a general space having
nothing to do with mechanics just a
general flow in any number of Dimensions
the general rule for an incompressible
flow would be that the derivative of the
I component of the
Velocity with respect to the i x is
equal to
zero right that's also written in the
notation some of I thank
you that's also written in the notation
that the
Divergence of V is equal to zero
Divergence simply means this act of
differentiating the I component with
respect to the I coordinate and summing
them up up and it's called the
Divergence
yeah I've assumed uniformity of the
density
yes yeah um if I hadn't assumed
uniformity of the density I just did
that to make it simpler had I not
assumed uniformity of the density what
you would have to do is invent a new
quantity which is the density at any
point times the
velocity and then that would be the
thing which would have zero Divergence
but if the density is uniform then that
factors
out so just for Simplicity I imagined
that the uh and after all if it's an
incompressible fluid it stands to reason
that its density is everywhere as the
same since you can't change its
density
so
um let's come back to phase base what
are the X's the X's are are just the
coordinates in some space in the case of
phase space the coordinates are the p's
and
q's right the p's and q's are the
coordinates so we should
identify the X's not just with q but
with a p and a q so the number of
x's is twice the number of Q's One One X
for each P and Q that's the space we're
dealing with if there's only one Q then
it's a two-dimensional space one p and
one q and so
forth right what are these quantities
over here Pabi Dot and qabi Dot those
are the local velocities in the phase
space they are the v
subis i now goes from 1 to 2 N it runs
over all of the coordinates in the
momenta but these are we could call this
here we could call it the
P sub
I the velocity along the axis P sub I
this we could call V Q
subi so the P dots and the Q dots are
the things that are being called the um
uh the velocity now let's calculate the
Divergence of the
flow we're going to calculate the
Divergence of the flow and of course
what we're going to use is Hamilton's
equations to see that the Divergence of
the flow is exactly zero all right so
the Divergence of the flow we take v p
subi and we differentiate it with
respect to P
subi so let's uh let's write the
Divergence of the flow over
here first of all we have derivative
of the
P I'm not going to bother writing the I
well maybe I should no let's let's let's
just do it for two Dimensions first then
we'll come back and talk about it for
any number derivative of VP with respect
to p with only one p and 1
Q what is that well that is equal to the
derivative with respect to
P times VP but VP is minus the
derivative of H with respect to
Q all right that's the first term what's
the second term in the Divergence the
second term is just DV
Q by
DQ all right what is VQ that's over here
plus DH by DP so this becomes d by
DQ of
plus DH by
DP if we have several coordinates in
momenta then we would put an i here and
some over
I
everywhere also in the lower equation
here I won't bother with it though well
now you can see what
happens partial derivatives can be
interchanged the derivative with respect
to p of the derivative with respect to Q
is the same as the derivative with
respect to Q of the derivative with
respect to P the P the Q is the same as
DQ DP it doesn't matter which order you
differentiate something in right this
one has a minus sign this one has a plus
sign so these cancel and
pairs they cancel and
pairs in fact it's not just that the
Divergence is equal to zero it's equal
to Z Z in a special way where they
cancel in pairs but that's okay the
Divergence the sum of these the
P that's exactly equal to
zero okay so the sum of these add them
together that's exactly equal to
zero and that proves that the flow in
Phase space is
incompressible
that is a quite a profound theorem about
uh about mechanics the incompressibility
of the flow the fact that uh the phase
points can't get squeezed into a smaller
volume that they maintain sort of they
have elbows and they keep uh from
running into each
other that is probably the most
important uh fact about hamiltonian
mechanics that it is this incompressible
kind of
flow
uh let's concentrate for a little while
on two Dimensions one p and one
Q remember this does not say that the
distance between
points stays the
same as I said what it
says is that the volume of a region of
phase space says same so a region like
this could flow into a region that looks
like
this as long as the volume stays the
same and in particular two points which
are fairly close can get fairly
far so there's no conservation of the
distance between points in the phase
space only the volume only the volume of
a of a patch of phase
space
um this idea
that let's take the two-dimensional case
that area is the important thing and not
distance you can see in another
way let's take the world's simplest
mechanical system a particle moving
along one axis with an energy which is x
do^ s a kinetic energy which is x do^ 2
over 2 I have even gone so far as to set
the mass equal to one to make it
simple
right there's a canonical momentum P sub
X which is equal to the derivative this
is the L grangian
lran is x do^ 2 over 2 the momentum
canonically conjugate to X is the
derivative of the lran with respect to x
dot and that's just x
dot now I could have used other core
another coordinate I didn't have to use
x to describe the system what would have
happened had I used
2x suppose I defined a new variable let
me call it y it does not stand for
another axis it just stands for another
representation of exactly the same
physics
uh a new
coordinate I'll Define and let's call it
Alpha time x
Alpha is just any number fixed could be
two it could be a half it could be seven
whatever it is this is just another
representation of the same uh system
where it's been labeled by a different
Axis or an axis with a either closer or
further points points uh different units
it really comes down to a unit
transformation okay uh what is x dot X
first of all is equal to Y over Alpha
and x dot is just equal to Y dot over
Alpha let's rewrite the lran the LAN
doesn't change lran is the same
numerical quantity no matter what
coordinates we use
lran will now
become X it's still x do^ 2 over two but
that becomes now y dot
2ar over twice Alpha squ
I've just written that x do^ 2 is y^2
alpha s that's the Newan it's just
another description of exactly the same
system what is the canonical momentum
conjugate to
Y well it's DL by Dy dot P sub
y is
equal to Y dot over Alpha
squar
okay let me now
write right over here we have y = Alpha
*
X we have py = y do over Alpha squared
but that's also equal to x dot over
Alpha I've used that y dot is equal to x
dot let's see what if I written yes y
dot is Alpha * x dot so wherever you see
y dot here just stick Alpha * x dot that
cancels one factor of
alpha all right but this is also equal
to P
subx over
Alpha all right so let me combine that
with this equation over here P sub y is
equal to P subx /
Alpha notice what's happened when you
make a coordinate
transformation that stretches the
xais it
shrinks the P axis sorry P yeah if you
make a transformation which stretches
the x-axis remember now X and Y are not
different directions of space they're
just different coordinates describing
the same thing this is a coordinate
transformation Y is equal to alpha x
along with it goes a transformation of
the canonical momentum but in the
opposite direction if you stretch the
x-axis you shrink the P
AIS okay that means for example if you
take the phase bace let's we can
represent it either in terms of X or
Y and we take a little region let's call
this X and
PX right suppose we represent that same
system in terms of y and p sub y
well the um the width of this box as
measured in y
units is Alpha times as big as it was in
X units but on the other hand the height
of the region is 1 over Alpha times what
it was in X units so whether the the
height of this box and the width of this
box as measured in either X or Y are not
the same but the area of the box as
measured in X and Y are the same this is
a characteristic feature of classical
mechanics that the various coordinate
Transformations that you would do if
combined you do some coordinate
transformation but you also calculate
what happens to the canonical
momenta you what you'll find mind is
that areas in the phase space always
stay the same so the idea of an element
of area in Phase space is very
fundamental it of course comes up in
quantum mechanics in quantum mechanics
it's basically roughly speaking the
statement that there's a smallest area
in Phase space a Quantum of area in
Phase space we'll come to that but not
I'll just mention it now that things
cannot be localized in the phase space
better than that Quantum of area how big
is the Quantum of
area plks
constant no no not squared not squared
plunks constant is not a measure of
Delta X or Delta P it's a measure of
area in the phase
space okay and it says that there's a
fundamental unit of area in the phase
space and that you cannot think of
anything smaller than that that's the
uncertainty principle Yeah
question
absolutely
absolutely the mathematical statement is
that the time evolution of a system is a
canonical
transformation
yeah that did or did not what say it
again why does the uh why does it not
conserve
energy no it loses it loses potential
energy gains kinetic
energy right
um good okay so
let's all right the statement the
statement that the flow in Phase space
flow in Phase space is
incompressible that's called Le ail's
theorem so you ago
thees where where where here no this
wasn't representing the time dependence
of anything this was just two different
sets of coordinates that's all it
could
well uh that call this is a canonical
transformation okay yeah
yeah right and we haven't we haven't
discussed that at the moment but
but the answer is yes that is a
canonical
transformation all the interesting
transformations of mechanics are called
canonical but we haven't defined them
yet so let's
uh all right let's talk a little bit
since it's been raised about what chaos
means
that's
right it means the
area in quantum mechanics it's of course
connected with the uncertainty
principle
uh that's
right
a p Dot and a q
dot P Dot and a q dot you want to
multiply P do times a q
dot okay let's multiply a p Dot and a q
dot what doesn't change is Delta P *
Delta Q the area of a little region of
face of face space it doesn't change you
have you
have X and p p subx and you have some
other
coordinates which you can call y and p
sub
y and if you calculate the take a little
region of area here break it up and
calculate its area by adding up the
squares and giving them and assigning
them an area Delta P sorry Delta x *
Delta P
subx or add them up by assigning them
Delta y * Delta P sub y you'll get the
same
answer so it's the area
element the size of an
area which will be the same in whatever
coordinates you use whatever coordinates
and momenta if the coordinates and
momenta come from the same
lran okay so yes so area area has an
invariant meaning in the phase
space
uh it takes on its sharpest physical
meaning when we get to Quantum Mechanics
where it really corresponds to the
uncertainty
principle well I don't know I I um what
does it
mean the fact that it's conserved means
that it's
useful uh that uh
that yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah it it
it tells you what the right probability
measure is on the phase space that an
invariant probability measure on the
phase
space and that's useful in statistical
mechanics
yeah yeah and uh it
uh for example for example if you have
some chaotic system there a phase bace
so that means the phase Point moves
around and gets you know really moves
around in some wild
way uh and you ask how often or what is
the
probability that is found in a little
region of phas space then the answer
will depend only on the area of the
region of phas
space
uh so area would be the thing which
would tell you the relative probab if
you are interested in the relative
probability probability could mean the
amount of time spent in this little
region here the phase Point moves
around goes crazy we stand there and
watch it and ask how much time does it
spend in that little volume that's a
measure of the probability that you
would find it in that volume versus this
volume all right the
answer is is that the relative
probability of being in two different
volumes of phase space is simply the
ratio of the
areas
right that's for a chaotic system for a
chaotic system yeah for a chaotic system
yes
right well here I'm defining
probabilities not by expectations your
your naive expectations I'm defining it
by the amount of time integrated time
that it spends in a region so that's a
that's a
stronger
yeah
right the the yeah the um the amount of
time that it's in here divided by the
total time that you sample the system
tends to a finite limit for chaotic
systems
yeah
right no yeah yes no it probably does
but I have to think about
it
no I'm not sure what the word stochastic
means frankly I think it just means an
element of
Randomness uh what does stochastic what
does the word stochastic
mean non non-
deterministic yeah well of course
chaotic systems are secretly
deterministic but you can't follow them
very long in time whe unless you have um
a degree of precision Which is far
beyond what uh what's reasonable I don't
want to I don't want to get into chaos
too much right now I will just tell you
very quickly one other thing about
chaotic systems or the difference
between chaotic and not chaotic both of
them have the feature that the phase
space volume stays the same but that
seems a little odd because you would
think that for systems which are
chaotic you know just um systems banging
into each other in random collisions not
random really but governed by the
equations of motion but nevertheless
complicated enough that they seem to
scatter all over the place you would
think that the phase Space volume
increases increases because you get
because after a while you know less and
less about where the system is
well that's not exactly true here's the
way it
works supposing you
take all right so the correct statement
is that this little sphere in Phase
space will evolve and it will evolve
into something which may look more or
less like a sphere but it may also look
uh you know grow all kinds of
complicated fibers and become very
fractal I don't know is fractal the word
probably
not you know start to grow
uh okay now here's what you
do
you I want to put some more
in okay Etc all right now if I literally
mathematically
follow the points
incidentally this will be just as
continuous as this if you look at it
under a microscope you will discover
that this phase space is completely
continuous nothing uh discontinuous is
broken off it or anything like that but
as time goes on it tends to get more and
more fractured like this let's just call
it
fractured if you take each point each
point goes to a definite point if you
follow the volume you'll find the volume
is the same but now you can do something
which is called course
graining coar graining means a
purposeful decision to draw little
circles or spheres around phase
points and roughly speaking what it
corresponds to is saying I don't have
enough Precision to be able to
distinguish points of phase space
strictly speaking I can only distinguish
this little volume from that little
volume from that little volume and that
little volume so what we do is draw
little spheres around each phase point
and follow the little spheres rather
than the individual phase
points follow the Spheres and what will
happen is this the sphere may go over
here the sphere may go way over here
this one may go way over here this one
may go way over
here but if we were to take the total
area occupied by these
spheres I think it's pretty obvious that
the total area will be much larger than
the area that you started with if this
thing branches out and
fractalized and it is so the coar
grained following of the phase space
allows the area to get bigger and bigger
and it does get bigger
yeah yeah because of the course graining
it's effectively random in other
words if you take the course grain phase
space the nasty thing that happens is no
matter how small a course graining is if
you wait long enough points within
one coarse grain here will separate and
get far outside a course
grain right if the co grain is defined
by little
spheres
so what's
that no no no then not the mapping from
the first no the mapping from the no no
no they're not the mapping from the
first they're just spheres in the face
Bas again spheres that you can
distinguish by the coar grained
apparatus that you happen to have so the
coar grained apparatus that you happen
to have defines a course graining on
here and it's not the same as the course
graining that would inherit by following
this course graining it's just what you
can measure what you can
distinguish uh and of course what you
can distinguish depends on the Precision
of your uh of your measuring apparatuses
and so forth but no matter
how precise your apparatuses and your
description
is no matter how small a course graining
here eventually points within a single
cell here of this Co graining will
diverge and get
outside the uh the corresponding Co
grain description of what happens later
that's what happens uh a chaotic system
most systems are chaotic of
course uh the uh the non-chaotic systems
which sort of maintain their their
integrity without in the course grain
sense those are rare and
exceptional
yeah say it
again yeah change in
time yeah
the area of the of the cor SC you you
take the original region of phas space
you figure out exactly what it does and
then in the original region of face
space you draw
spheres if the original
region is a nice simple sphere or
something like a sphere then when you
add up all of the uh these coarse grain
spheres you'll get the volume of the
original sphere back pretty much but now
you take this tree this very very um
finely fractalized tree that it grows
into which may fill up this very big
piece of this Blackboard with very fine
filaments very very close to each other
okay so for example if there are
filaments extremely close to each other
so close to each other that the coarse
graining
uh sort of slops over or slops over the
distinction between these different
filaments then the total volume of these
coar grained green spheres will in
general exceed the volume that you
started
with
why yeah it's basically just going to
cover this whole uh the whole tree there
yeah yeah you just yeah yeah yeah so you
just look at this picture with fuzzy
eyes and you see how big uh how big this
region is this region can be much much
bigger yeah
lots of
ways the
what yeah you're counting everything
within this little sphere here even
though the fiber in here may be much
thinner than the sphere but the fibers
are so thin that your apparatuses cannot
t tell exactly where you are in the
sphere all you know is you're somewhere
in the sphere so at the end of the day
if you ask where am I if I start in here
the answer to the question is you're
somewhere in here in a much bigger
region if you had infinite precise
control over the either the mathematics
or the measuring measurement then the
volume of this fiber um
ultra fine filamentary structure would
be exactly the same as the original ball
here but you don't follow things that
way that's not the way you follow things
in an experiment you say Okay I I I
detect the I detect a a particle
somewhere is in this phase region over
here I can't tell exactly where it is
because it requires too much
Precision so in that sense the phase
Space volume does expand
okay it's called course
graining and it is of course the origin
of the second law of
Thermodynamics okay there's one other
point that I should
emphasize uh I don't know when when and
if we'll come to it in a more thorough
way but the entropy of a system is a
measure of the volume in Phase space
that the system
occupies
uh the det the detectable volume in
Phase space meaning to say if you know
about a system that it's somewhere in
here you take that volume of phase space
that volume of phase space which
corresponds to the boundaries of the
region that uh that your knowledge tells
you that the system I'm getting I'm
getting tied up you have some knowledge
about the system the knowledge of the
system is that it's somewhere is in here
in this volume of phase BAS
the entropy is a direct measure of that
volume in fact it's the logarithm of
that
volume okay essentially that's now the
system evolves and what you know
afterwards is that it's somewhere is in
here you're not either clever enough or
precise enough to be able to distinguish
these fibers so all you know is that the
system is somewhere in here the face
base volume is bigger afterwards words
than it started in the
beginning because you haven't followed
the details sufficiently carefully to
know precisely to distinguish this bit
of fiber from that bit of
fiber that's why entropy
increases basically it's a statement
that when the phase space fragments like
this you lose information for not
because information is really lost but
because uh you have a hard time
following the system it's a
technological thing you can't follow
things with a sufficient
Precision okay that's
uh that's lille's
theorem as I said it is um extremely
fundamental to both classical mechanics
and its Evolution into quantum
mechanics what I wanted to do
next
completely different
direction was to work out the equations
of a particle we have not studied part
very many examples incidentally you'll
notice I want to study the example of a
particle moving in an electromagnetic
field there's one thing that's new in a
magnetic field that we haven't
encountered yet and it's the existence
of velocity dependent
forces so far the forces that we've imag
iMed depend on where you are but not how
you're moving when we said that there's
a potential energy function U of
X and we differentiate it to find the
force well the left hand side is just a
function of position so the force on a
system just depends on where you are
there are forces in nature which depend
on velocity magnetic magnetic field
acting on a particle is a prime
example incidentally friction is also an
example friction is an example where the
velocity of a where the force on an
object does depend on its velocity if
it's standing still there's no friction
Force if it's moving there is a friction
Force typically the faster it moves the
larger the force there's a fundamental
difference between magnetic forces and
friction forces and the simplest way to
say it is that forces due to make
magnetic fields although the velocity
dependent are derivable from a principle
of least
action they have a lran formulation
there's a conservation of energy and
there's a hamiltonian
formulation it's just that the lran and
hamiltonian have a new little twist of
them that uh that will that I want to
work out
now
forces due to Electric
Fields uh are no different than the
forces we've already studied uh I think
I'll come back to Electric Fields I want
to concentrate on magnetic fields
because there's a new phenomenon there
that uh that's
interesting all right so what is the
force of a particle uh if it's in a
magnetic field magnetic field is called
B it's a vector and it depends on
position B of X the magnetic field what
is the force of a Charged particle on a
Charged
particle V cross B well actually Q * V
cross B where Q is the charge of the
particle velocity cross magnetic field
it's a vector the cross product of two
vectors both of these are
vectors this is theoc velocity of the
particle this is the magnetic field and
so it says what uh everybody know what a
cross product is assume everybody more
that means yes or
no yeah
right right let's see
[Music]
um
right something to do with a
Thum I'm going to assume everybody knows
what a cross product is although will
Define
it okay so let's define the cross
product right now the cross product can
most easily be defined through its
components V has three components x y
and z b has three components X Y and Z
the cross product has three
components here's the rule the Z
component let's forget Q here and let's
just write the rule the Z component of
this
this What's called the Z component of it
V crossb the Z component of it is equal
to VX by
y
minus VY
BX I remember one one of them I remember
the Z component and then if I want any
of the other
components I just cycle Z goes to X goes
to y so the next one would be x v cross
B the X component and I cycle X goes to
y v y y goes to z v
z minus
minus v z b
y and the last
one V cross
B in the y
direction is equal to X1 y
z y z
x
minus
v x b z did I get that right I think I
got it
right okay that's the definition of a
cross
product now we need one other concept we
need the concept of the vector
potential the vector potential is simply
a way of writing magnetic
fields but you would think well if it's
just a way of writing the magnetic field
why not just use the magnetic
field and uh the answer is you cannot
write the mechanics of a Charged
particle just in terms of the magnetic
field you need the vector
potential uh you can of course write the
mechanics fals ma but you cannot write a
hamiltonian you cannot write a L
grangian you cannot write even an
expression for uh for canonical
momenta you need an auxilary quantity
called the vector potential and the
vector potential is just defined by the
condition that the magnetic field is the
curl of the vector
potential let's write down what curl
means because we'll need it
later the vector potential is also a
vector
magnetic field is a uh is a vector the
vector potential is a
vector what's special about things which
are are curls of other
things they have no Divergence and the
magnetic field is a thing which has no
Divergence and that's why it's
convenient to write it this way but for
our purposes let's imagine that the
vector potential is something
fundamental that we begin with with and
that the magnetic field is a derived
quantity we're going to see that the
mechanics of a Charged particle is best
written in terms of the vector potential
not the magnetic
field okay let's write down the
definition of cross
product a cross product
again can be defined by its
components Del cross a the Z component
of it now it's basically the same thing
except wherever you see a v up there
wherever you see a b stick an A and
wherever you see a v over there put an
upside down uh
Delta all right so this just says that
this is what is what does delta mean it
just means the collection of three
derivatives Delta X Delta Y and Delta Z
are just derivative with respect to X
the derivative with respect to Y and the
derivative with respect to Z I assume
you all know that kind of thing a little
bit of vector calculus but let's just
write down exact ly what this means this
means derivative with respect to X of a
sub y minus the derivative with respect
to Y of a
subx and then cycle it down Del cross a
the X component of it is the Y
derivative of a z minus the Z derivative
of a y and just cycle it down X goes to
y y goes to z z goes back to X X I won't
write them all down
so we can now write that the
force on a Charged particle due to the
magnetic
field is the charge time V cross
B which is also the charge time V cross
the curl of
a
I'm going to bore you a little more with
this by writing out the individual
components to by writing out the Z
component of force here it's a little
bit
tedious but we'll need
it we'll need the expression for the Z
component of force explicitly in terms
of the vector
potential so let's write it out this is
just an expression this is just an
exercise in
substituting all right I want the Z
component of the
force f
subz is equal to the
charge now the cross product we have the
cross product where is it we have the Z
component of V
crossb that's VX
by
minus
VY
BX but now let's just substitute in for
b y where is it um oh
brother
uh this is
Q VX now go to
um
[Music]
H by Y is
DZ
ax minus DX a
z that's the first
term
minus v
y time BX which is dy a
z minus DZ a
y well this is a fairly complicated
expression for the Z component of force
but if you know the vector
potential you can work out what this is
it's just some Vector field you can
multiply it by the velocities and you
can compute the force the Z component of
Force if you want the other components
again you just
cycle the
X X goes to y y goes to Z you just cycle
through all right that's the force on a
particle and the equation is just
Newton's equation f equals
ma but now the new thing is that the
acceleration doesn't only depend on the
position it does depend on the position
through the uh through the position
dependence of a but it also depends on
the velocity so these are called
velocity dependent forces of course they
depend on
velocity we want to formulate the theory
of a Charged particle moving in a
magnetic field in the lran or
hamiltonian form not obvious that we can
do it it is not obvious that this is of
the form uh that uh that allows us to
have a hamiltonian lran and so forth or
an action
principle the easiest way to confirm
that is just to make a guess at what the
action is and then follow it
through the new thing in the action well
first of
all we do
expect that if the electric charge was
Zero that there would be the usual terms
all right uh so let's write the action
let's make a guess for the action the
integral of the lran
DT well first of all guess has the
usual m v^ 2 over 2
DT where v^2 means the sums of the
squares of the X component y component
and Z component of the velocities the
usual thing this is what we would do for
a free particle and if the particle has
no electric charge it doesn't feel the
magnetic field and then there's another
term and the other term is as simple as
it could possibly be we take the orbit
of the charged particle we break it
up into to little
segments each segment we call
DX also Dy and DZ but let's just
abbreviate it by calling it
DX each little
segment defines a differential
displacement in DX Dy and
DZ the added
term that's first of all proportional to
the electric
charge if there's no magnetic field then
obviously viously there is no additional
term even if there is an electric charge
the extra term is related to both the
charge and the magnetic field but it's
related through the vector potential
where where's Vector potential did uh oh
boy did I erase the most important
equation I
did
okay I assume you all memorized what V
crossb looks like in terms of the vector
potential and you'll recognize it when I
write it down I didn't mean to erase it
all right what can you write down it's
going to have the vector potential in
it so let's call it a sub
I the simplest thing you can write down
is the integral the line integral of the
vector potential dotted into the
differential displacement DX in other
words what this means is every place in
space you have a vector potential
as the particle sweeps out through its
trajectory there's a contribution to its
action from each little differential
displacement here and the contribution
to the action is just take the dot
product of the vector potential with the
displacement in other words the
component of the vector potential along
the direction of the displacement and
add them all
up very simple prescription how do I
know that's the answer well know that's
the answer because it was written down
in the early parts of the 20th century
and I learned it as a
student yeah dxy good and or you can
just write a. DX where you can think of
both a and DX as little vectors one is a
little Vector the other is just a vector
all right a. DX can represent the
dotproduct of the vector potential with
the differential
displacement
it doesn't seem like units are working
out right is
time how do you know what the units are
do you know what the units of a are what
the units of Q
are a
[Music]
time but how can you tell me what the
units are unless we know what the units
of Q
are okay or a how do we know what the
units of a
are well the units of a and the units of
Q obviously the combination Q * a is the
important thing and the combination of Q
* a has units that are required to make
this have the same units as
that what are the units of an action
incidentally
or momentum times uh position sorry
momentum yeah momentum time
x uh no problem you can always give Q
the right dimensions this is correct
um uh in some appropriate choice of
units this is correct and it depends on
the on on the uh conventions in some
conventions there are pies floating
around or speeds of light but you can
set them all equal to one and since I'm
trying to describe a uh a phenomena
rather than a numerical effect let's
just set all the numerical constants
equal to one or to absorb them into the
electric charge
here okay now this is
yeah yes that's exactly what I was about
to do this does not have the usual form
of an action which depends on velocities
and
positions the A's depend on position as
a rule but what is this DX here
here all we have to do is divide and
multiply by
DT DX by DT that's just the X component
of the Velocity right so we can also
write this
as uh a dotted into the
velocity integral
DT or I can write it in terms of
components uh a sub I
X subi do DT and now we see the usual
form the what's it some over I yeah Su
over
I all right so we see and this of course
is also XI do
s sum over I I'm not going to write
it all right so we have then a typical
lran we can write out now what the lran
is and it depends on position and
velocity the way any respectable lran
would L grangian for a particle in a
magnetic field is 12 the mass of the
particle time x sub I do squared where I
goes over X Y and
Z
sum
Plus Q the charge of a
particle x subi
dot times the vector potential a
subi what's the next step the next step
is to prove that the equation of motion
for this object is f equals ma with the
right hand side
being where is it QV V cross
B
F = Q V cross
B if we can do that if we can now take
the lrange equations here's the lran
take the lrange equations and see if we
can prove that the force on a particle
this is equal to mass time acceleration
that this is equal to QV cross P if we
can do that then we're finished we found
the lran form ulation of particle in a
magnetic
field so this is now an exercise in just
plugging it
through I could tell you to go home and
do it but let's do it let's just carry
it
out there is one Curious Thing coming up
that we'll see in a
second first of all what is the
canonical
momentum piece of
X well it's the derivative of the Lan
with respect to x dot so let's take the
X component I now mean the X component
we could write down Y and Z also that's
going to be
m x dot from
here usual
thing normal momentum but then there's
another term plus q a
subx and of course the same kind of
thing for py and
pz so we have a system now where the
canonical momentum is not just m * V
it's m * V plus something proportional
to the vector
potential
um sometimes M * x dot is called the
mechanical
momentum it's sometimes called the
mechanical momentum meaning to say you
know it's meaning to say nothing other
than that it's mass times velocity and
the whole thing is called the canonical
momentum all right so that's that's one
new thing here we see something new that
the there's a discrepancy between the
canonical momentum and what we naively
think of as
momentum okay but now let's work out the
equation of
motion let's work out the Z component we
can know there's three of these but
let's get the pz is equal to m Z dot
plus q a
subz I'm going to work out the Z
component of equation of motion what is
it it's the time derivative of the
momentum I'll just write down over here
D by
DT of DL by DZ dot is equal to DL by
DZ DL by DZ dot that's just
pz
okay so we have to take the time
derivative of this thing here let's
write down the time derivative it's
m z double dot that's masstimes
acceleration and then there's another
term in the time derivative of pz it's
plus Q time the time derivative of a
z now in a moment we'll come back and
work out what the time derivative of a z
is but let's go to the right hand side
of the
equation the right hand side of the
equation is the derivative of the lran
with respect to
Z what is it that depends on Z in here x
do or Z dot doesn't depend on
z a a and all of the A's a x a y and a z
all depend on uh on uh on on Z in
general so let's go through
them
Q now the first term here would be x dot
time a
subx so we would get a term which would
be x dot times the derivative of a subx
with respect to Z remember we're taking
derivative of the lran with respect to Z
the only thing that depends on Z are the
three components of a let's start with
the X component X do ax and
differentiate it with respect to Z the
next one is
plus y dot times the derivative of a y
with respect to
Z and what's the last one Z dot times
the derivative of a subz with respect to
Z
okay all I did was differentiate all
three terms here with respect to
Z each one of them depends on Z through
the components
a what about the left hand side what do
I do with a subz
dot let's suppose incidentally that it's
just a static magnetic field magnetic
field not changing with time it's just a
fixed magnetic field does that mean that
this is
zero if it's a fixed magnetic
field
no no because the particle moves through
the magnetic field I don't mean when I
say it's a fixed magnetic field I don't
mean it's the same everywhere as in
space I mean it doesn't depend on time
magnetic field varies from place to
place particle moves through it and
because the particle moves through it
there's a Time dependence of the
magnetic field of the ve Vector
potential at the point of the particle
so how do we calculate that well we
simply write
m z do plus
Q now a
z depends on x d a z by DX time x
dot plus the a
y sorry what are we doing here yes sorry
the the a z sorry a z a z we're
calculating AZ dot which is the
derivative of a with respect to x times
the time rate of change of
X plus the a z by
Dy * y dot plus d a z by d
z time Z
dot that's equal to what's in the
bracket over
here
equals
this
okay I'll let you stare at it for a
minute remember the right hand side came
from explicitly differentiating the lran
with respect to Z the leftand side came
from differentiating with respect to T
but notice they have similar form each
one here has a velocity time a
derivative of a on both sides so maybe
they combine together in some nice
way well first of
all you'll see that this term and this
term are the same Z dot time d a z by
DZ they're the same so they
cancel let's get rid of
them now what's left let's look at what
multiplies x dot x dot has D ax by
DZ and then when we shift to the other
side it will have
what d a z by
DX so it's going to
have Let's
uh let's move this
over now I forgot what it
was plus y dot what was
it d a y by
DZ
yeah partial a y with respect to Z right
yeah okay now what the term which
multiplies x
dot when I transpose it it's going to
have minus d a z by
DX oh that's starting to look
familiar and when I transpose the term
that has y dot in it that will have
minus d a z by
Dy
I've transposed this term over to the
right hand side and I now have MZ dot or
mass
times the Z component of
acceleration is equal to this mess over
here well what is this mess this mess is
not so complicated
it's got linear terms in the velocities
and what are these
objects the magnetic field the curl of
the vector potential in fact this one is
um ax1 I think this is b y is it b y or
minus b
y and this one I think is minus uh
BX the X dots and Y dots are the
components of the velocity
if you go through it or just go back in
your notes to where I wrote it down in
the beginning this is just the Z
component of V cross B velocity
H yeah
okay
right VX time
DZ ax minus DX a z and so forth
yeah okay so you see that first of all
there does exist a lran formulation here
it is for particle in a magnetic
field you need to know the vector
potential first question is the vector
potential unique in terms of the
magnetic
field no you can add things to the
vector potential we'll come to that but
not right now but if you know the vector
potential or you know a particular
expression for the V Vector potential
then you can write down the lran you can
the Lan depends on the vector
potential but the equation of motion
only depends on the magnetic field so
even if there is an ambiguity in the
vector potential it doesn't affect the
equation of motion
itself
okay now we have an example of a
velocity dependent force and Force which
is V crossb it's almost like a friction
force it is
different the friction Force acts along
the direction of the
Velocity okay if an object is moving in
this direction the friction force is
along the same axis what about V cross
B does v crossb act along the direction
of the Velocity no because V cross B is
perpendicular to to both the velocity
and to B so this and this is a big
difference a big difference uh whether
the whether the velocity dependent Force
acts along the direction of velocity or
perpendicular to it if it acts along the
direction of velocity it will obviously
have the effect of either slowing it
down or speeding it up depending on
which way it it's acting all right but
if it acts perpendicular to the velocity
it'll simply change the direction of the
Vel
velocity if the force is perpendicular
and it won't change the energy so energy
conservation will we can work out now we
can work out what is the expression for
the energy we do that by calculating the
hamiltonian and when we've calculated
the hamiltonian we then have from
previous theorems the theorem that says
that energy is
conserved right so we can work that out
let's work it
out I think we're I think we'll just
that'll just about take us to the end of
the the hour oh excuse me there's
something I need to tell
you I won't be here for the next uh two
lectures now I would like to make up one
of them I think
uh the question is what is a good time
it could be this week yet but it can't
be next week and it could be the week
after but not on
Monday uh yeah we can do it this week
does that uh does that work out for
people if would do it say
Thursday Friday is a bad day for me or
we can put it off we can put it off till
I get back and uh and uh
uh uh just double up the week that I
come back I'll be gone
for
H should we wait until
uh to take it Thursday
Thursday how many cannot take it
Thursday well that's all that's almost
half the class
uh supposing I were to put it off I'll
be back on the 11th now the 11th uh is
probably a Monday uh no 11th is a
Tuesday wnes H yeah I was thinking about
Wednesday the 12th I think it
is is it 12th or 13th 12 does that work
no get something I know
that well we can stay on Monday and uh
but
uh yeah no we'll continue we'll continue
but at some point uh we uh we run into
the next
quarter I you
know playing you know points have to
move rigidly
uh can't
uh well we could do that another thing I
have to do as I'm supposed to uh fill in
the missing lecture from the first uh
the first lecture I was thinking of
doing that this week but
uh no no no they we didn't miss a
lecture but they didn't
uh they didn't um film
it
what's
that no doesn't have to be no
no I'm happy to this is fun for me I
just do it for the fun of it uh no we no
I intend to keep going until the uh
until sometime near
Christmas um but uh we will miss the
next two lectures so I thought I would
try to make up
one what's
that yeah two
Mondays but then we'll be back on
Monday well we will be back on Monday
and we'll see if we need if we need to
fill in if we need to fill in with
another lecture we'll just figure out at
that point when to fill in we're
already well I don't think we we'll do
Christmas
Eve
uh
that's
yeah yeah we well look why don't we just
decide this when I get back on the uh on
the 17th we'll try we'll see when we can
fill in an extra lecture and I think
that'll pretty much bring us to where we
want to be I mean I'm pretty
comfortable
yeah uh three weeks yes three weeks from
today right right right right next
lecture is the
17th
um okay let's try to just finish up what
I was talking about here I thought I
think I finished
um energy yeah okay let's do
energy so all we have to do is calculate
the
hamiltonian incidentally I'm assuming
that the vector potential has no
explicit time
dependence in other words equivalently
that the magnetic field is constant in
time in that case the hamiltonian will
be time independent and there will be a
conserved energy the conserved energy is
surprisingly simple when expressed in
terms of the Velocity is a little more
complicated when expressed in terms of
the momenta so let's work it out let's
first calculate uh
uh p subx as we saw before was MX
dot plus q a sub X same thing for Y and
Z and I won't bother writing them down
separately okay the first thing we have
to do when we calculate the
hamiltonian actually we don't need to we
can just let's let's calculate it not in
terms of P but in terms of x dot let's
first do it by calculating in terms of
velocities to see what the expression
for energy is in terms of velocities all
right so what do we have to calculate we
have to calculate p subx x dot plus p
suby y dot plus p subz z dot minus the
lran
right that's the definition of
h take each momenta multiply it by the
corresponding velocity and then subtract
the lran that's a very general rule that
we derived right if I plug in for the
P's their expression in terms of
velocities I'll have an expression for
the energy in terms of
velocities that won't be good for
Hamilton's equations but it will be good
for telling me what the energy is in
terms of
velocities so let's do that let's do
that first p subx x x dot that
is m x dot + q a
subx time x
dot likewise for Y and Z and I won't
write them
out then we have to subtract off the
lran minus l so subtracting off the lran
means subtracting off minus
M v^2 or MX do2 I'm concentrating on the
X term M MX do
uh divided by
two and then what
else
minus
Q X do a
subx well that gives me mx. S over two
the usual
thing no difference
there and look at this Q axx do minus Q
axx do they cancel
completely so the expression for the
energy is exactly just the original
kinetic
energy just MX do^ 2 over two likewise
for y and
z
the magnetic field does not contribute
to the energy when expressed in terms of
velocities it's just 12 mv^ squared end
of story now why is that why is that
that's equivalent to another statement
it's equivalent to the statement that
magnetic fields do no
work what's that yeah that's right it's
because the force is perpendicular to
the velocity
so when a particle moves in a magnetic
field the force is perpendicular to the
velocity the force being perpendicular
to the velocity means that the magnitude
of the Velocity doesn't
change right a force perpendicular to a
velocity deflects an object but doesn't
change its
velocity uh
and
so as the particle moves along its
direction may change change but its
speed doesn't so it's the original
expression for its energy in terms of
mx. s is just the full energy magnetic
fields do no work which is the same
statement as a statement that the energy
when expressed in terms of velocities
and so forth is exactly the same as it
was in the first place 1 12 mv^2 is
conserved and you know how particles
move in a magnetic field for example if
there's a uniform magnetic field into
the Blackboard particles move in
circular orbits with uniform speed so
the kinetic energy is
conserved that's statement number one
but in this form you cannot use the
hamiltonian to write down Hamilton's
equations you have to express it in
terms of um in terms of the momenta but
that's easy all we have to do is solve
for the X dots in terms of the momenta
that's easy X x dot is just P subx - q a
subx /
M so we can write down immediately what
the hamiltonian is in terms of P's
instead of in Terms of X dots and it's
just
equal the P
subx minus q a
subx
squared over
M2
over 2 m^2 excuse
me I've just substituted for the
velocity their expression in terms of
the
momenta
yeah no it does well it it
accelerates oh it does it does it does
but radiation is a higher order effect
that that's only important when the
particles uh when yeah it does uh
it certainly does
radiate right but thus far we have not
even tried to think about radiation in
order to understand
radiation we would have to formulate
Maxwell's equations and formulate them
in a hamiltonian form and discover that
the radiation field itself has
energy yeah
um right
so yeah this is the radiationless
approximation
mean these yeah sure
absolutely plus Z
term right so it's a little bit odd and
a little bit
surprising that when expressed in terms
of velocities the energy just doesn't
change but when expressed in terms of
canonical
momenta the expression for the energy
does
change and now if we applied Hamilton's
equations to this expression here we
would again get precisely the same uh uh
equations of
motion what's
that yeah yeah all you do is replace the
canonical moment the momentum
by the momentum minus q a subx in other
words this is just a mechanical momentum
here the MX do
term the mechanical momentum and the
canonical momentum differ by Q * a the
energy is just mx. s so it's just a
mechanical you know just the uh the
square of the mechanical momentum but
you substitute the canonical momentum if
you want to do Hamilton's equations so
here's an exercise take this hamiltonian
work out Hamilton's equations and check
that you get the same equations of
motion
uh mass time acceleration is equal to V
crossb that's a that's a homework
assignment
[Music]
okay the proceeding program is
copyrighted by Stanford University
please visit us at stanford.
EDU